A priori or a טוען וחוזר וטוען,
toein vechozer
vetoien, right?
I mean all of those things have to be considered, yeah.
Those two things seem to be the flip side of each other.
Well, it is true that the idea of טוען וחוזר וטוען toein
vechozer vetoien is almost like the theoretical idea of מיגו. migo. מיגו
migo is I could have said something else and טוען toein is
I'm actually saying something else. So yes, those are somewhat of the
flip side. Yeah, that's true, that's true, there is some parallel between
that. Okay. Now we're going to lead into actually a direct addressing
explicitly of this טוען וחוזר וטוען toein vechozer vetoien idea. זה אומר
של אבותי וזה אומר של אבותי. zeh omer shelo avotai vezeh omer
shelo avotai. Okay, this time it'll be דוד David and me fighting.
Okay, so דוד David says, this field was my ancestral plot. Okay,
and I say, what? דוד, David, yes. Oh, we're going in order.
We're going in order. Okay, and then I say, I'm not fighting
you, you are going to kill me in court, I'm fighting דוד.
David. Okay anyway. So he says, this field has been my ancestral
plot, and I'm saying, what are you talking about? This field was
my ancestral plot, של אבותי. shelo avotai. Okay, זה אומר של אבותי
וזה אומר של אבותי. zeh omer shelo avotai vezeh omer shelo avotai.
האי אייתי סהדי דאבותי היא. hai ayiti sahadai davoti hi. דוד David
brings witnesses that shows that his parents, his father, his whatever, grandfather,
we'll see in a minute anyway, had been living there and presumably
doing their חזקה chazakah years, okay? והאי אייתי סהדי דאכלה שני חזקה.
vehai ayiti sahadai deachlah shenei chazakah. Now I did not have evidence
to back up directly my claim that it was my ancestral plot.
What I do have evidence is that I've been here for the
last three years.
Okay. Now אמר רבא, amar Rava, now we get to the מיגו
migo case. מה לי לשקר? mah lo leshaker?
Why should I be believed to say that it's my ancestral plot?
Because here I know דוד's David claim from the very beginning. We're
coming to court, דוד David says it's my ancestral plot. Now if
I were smart, if I were willing to lie and I were
smart, I would not have competed with him whether whose ancestral plot
it was, I would have just said I bought it, and here's
my עדי חזקה. edei chazakah. So that's if I were, you know,
dishonest and smart. The fact that I didn't say that and I
said it was my forefather, you know, my ancestral plot, I should
be believed because I could have won with a better claim that
would have won against his עדים. edim. So it says, אמר ליה,
amar leh, so אמר רבא, amar Rava, מה לי לשקר, mah lo
leshaker, which is another way of saying, you know, מיגו. migo. What
incentive do I have to lie? אי בעי אמרי ליה מינך זבינתה
דאכלתה שני חזקה. ee ba'ei amina leh minach zevintai deachalteih shenei chazakah.
I exactly could have said, דוד, David, I bought it from you,
here are my עדים. edim. So even though I am, so even
though I'm not saying that, I should have the same power of
that claim. And therefore I should be believed in my claim that
it's my ancestral plot because I could have had a claim that
would have won. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה אביי,
amar leh Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back to רבא, Rava, מה
לי לשקר במקום עדים לא אמרינן. mah lo leshaker bimkom edim lo
amrinan. No, no, no. מיגו, migo, מה לי לשקר mah lo leshaker
doesn't win out against עדים edim because think what I have to
say. I have to say, you have witnesses that it's your ancestral
plot. I am going to be believed against your witnesses because if
I were lying I could have said something else. Okay, but I'm
asking the court to believe me over the direct testimony of witnesses.
And we know, you know, halakhically, I mean, okay, you know, that
witnesses are considered to be iron-clad evidence. Right? It doesn't mean like
we don't imagine it's theoretically possible that they're lying. Obviously we do.
There's a whole פרשה parsha of עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Okay, but
in a formal sense, we have, they are given the most weight
possible. So therefore how could I win over witnesses even though, you
know, okay, maybe I'm, you know, who knows, maybe I'm not smart
enough to know how to lie well or whatever. But how could
that, you know, even, but how could that beat witnesses? So אמר
ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, מה לי לשקר במקום עדים לא אמרינן.
mah lo leshaker bimkom edim lo amrinan. Witnesses are the strongest, my
claim that it's my ancestral will cannot beat your witnesses who say
that it's your ancestral plot. הדר אמר ליה, hadar amar leh, אין,
in, דאבתך היא. davatech hi. You know what, דוד? David? You're right.
It is your forefather's plot.
Okay, וזבינתה מינך vezavinteh minach and I actually bought it from you
and here's my witnesses. Because actually we were sitting in the case,
apparently אביי Abaye and רבא Rava were our דיינים, dayanim, okay? They
were having this discussion. רבא Rava said, oh, we should give it
to דב. Dov. And רבא Rava said, no we can't. מה לי
לשקר mah lo leshaker doesn't work. So I'm saying, oh, so now
I'm listening and I'm saying, oh wait a minute, he just said
that if I would have said that I had actually bought it
and here's my חזקה chazakah witnesses I would have won. Oh, you
know what? Actually that is what happened. Okay. I actually did buy
it. It was your forefather's and I actually did buy it from
you and here's my חזקה. chazakah. That now that sounds like a
טוען וחוזר וטוען. toein vechozer vetoien. Now you understand the problem with
that, right? Even though I've got witnesses, right? אמר ליה, amar leh,
אין דאבתך היא וזבינתה מינך. in davatech hi vezavinteh minach. And I
bought it from you. והאי דאמרי לך דדאבותי
היא, vehai deamri lach dedavatei hi, that I said it was my
forefather's ancestral, I didn't mean that literally. דסמיך לי עלה כדאבותי. desmich
li aleh kedavatei.
I felt so confident in it as if it had been something
that was always my ancestral plot. I was not being so literal.
Don't do that, not you. Yeah, don't take me so... literally. Okay,
so is that legitimate now? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so
what's the story? טוען וחוזר וטוען או אין טוען וחוזר וטוען. Toein
vechozer vetoien o ein toein vechozer vetoien. Can you make a claim
and then make a different claim? Or can you not do that?
Okay, and obviously the point is, you know, on the one hand
it's going to be obvious that if all you're doing is clarifying
something which is a clear clarification, like the case before, חזקה Chazakah
years doesn't mean only three, you know, it could mean minimum three.
That's not a big deal. Okay, on the other hand if you're
saying something that is a clear contradiction—I bought it from you January
1st, 2017 and now I'm saying I bought it from you January
1st, 2010—okay, a clear contradiction, that you can't do. The question is
the stuff in the middle where it's like a stretch to believe
that's what you mean, but it's not necessarily out of the realm
of possibility. Will we be open to that reinterpretation or to that,
you know, revise me, revising of your claim? טוען וחוזר וטוען או
אין טוען וחוזר וטוען? Toein vechozer vetoien o ein toein vechozer vetoien?
עולא Ulla אמר amar טוען וחוזר וטוען. toein vechozer vetoien. You can
do that. נהרדעי Nahardei אמרי amri אינו טוען וחוזר וטוען. eino toein
vechozer vetoien. You cannot revise your claim when there's a, when there's
what seems to be a strong contradiction to what you said before.
Now, ומודי עולא, Umodi Ulla, now we're going to sort of talk
about how again it's not like an absolute debate, there are middle
cases. ומודי עולא, Umodi Ulla, now עולא Ulla will concede, who says
you can revise your claim, היכא דאמר ליה של אבותיי ולא של
אבותיך, heicha de'amar lei shel avotai velo shel avotecha, ואינו טוען וחוזר
וטוען. ve'eino toein vechozer vetoien. If I had said to David, it's
my forefathers', not your forefathers', and then I said, okay, you know
what, it is your forefathers', I just meant that I feel really
confident about it like... no, that clearly is contradicting what I said
before, we throw that out. Okay, ואינו טוען וחוזר וטוען. ve'eino toein
vechozer vetoien. והיכא דקאי בבי דינא ולא טען, veheicha deka'ei bebei dina
velo ta'an, now even again עולא Ulla that says I can revise
when it's not a direct contradiction. So we were in court, we
were arguing it, and I did not revise. Then ואזל מאבראי, ve'azal
me'abrai, then I came from the outside. Then I said, okay, you
know what, we're going to take an hour break for lunch, and
after the hour break for lunch I came back into the court
case and all of a sudden I said, you know what, I
want to revise what I was saying before. Okay, וטען, veta'an, now
I have a new claim and I'm reinterpreting whatever what I said
before, אינו חוזר וטוען. eino chozer vetoien. That will not be accepted.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why? וטען... Veta'an... no, no, I made a
claim, אבותיי היא. avotai hi. Then we took a lunch... and I
was going to lose the case. Then we took a lunch break,
then after the lunch break I came back and I said I
didn't mean אבותיי, avotai, I meant I bought it from you but
סמיך עליה כאבותיי. samich alei ka'avotai.
That's והיכא
דקאי בבי דינא ולא טען.
veheicha deka'ei bebei dina velo ta'an. Oh, לא טען lo ta'an means
the revision.
I mean, I understand, it's a little bit unclear, but it
means ולא חוזר וטוען. velo chozer vetoien. Okay, I know, I hear
your problem, but that's what it means. Okay, וטען אינו חוזר וטוען.
veta'an eino chozer vetoien. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why? טענייה אגמריה. Tanyei agmarei.
I was taught how to revise it. I had a moment to
confer with my lawyer, and then I came back, so obviously if
there's some sense now, you know, that I revised it... so the
case I drew a moment ago, which is I overheard אביי Abaye
and רבא Rava talking and I heard them say, oh, if he
would have said he had bought it then he would have won,
and then I said something, presumably then actually even according to עולא
Ulla I wouldn't be believed because then again I'm being instructed, you
know, not necessarily intentionally, but I'm being instructed what how to revise
my claim. So therefore even עולא Ulla that says you can revise
your claim, that's when we are not concerned that you were actually
being instructed how to do this. So there's at least the possibility
that there's some sincerity and some judgment about what you're... about what?
Takes long?
Yeah, I'm going to ask David in a moment about this. But
let's first finish this גמרא. Gemara.
Like taking a move back in chess?
Yeah, but you
can do that or not.
Right, right, right, you have to keep your finger on it. Okay.
So, alright. So anyway, so I can't... so again, if I can't
directly contradict, I can do a strong revision and reinterpretation, but not
if there's reason to suspect that somebody was advising me about this.
Okay. Now, ומודי נהרדעי, Umodi Nahardei, now נהרדעי Nahardei who says you
cannot be חוזר וטוען, chozer vetoien, they admit היכא דאמר ליה של
אבותיי שלקחוה מאבותיך דחוזר
וטוען. heicha de'amar lei shel avotai shelakchuha me'avotecha dechozer vetoien. Let's say
with my debate here with David, I actually am making a revision
which somewhat like the גמרא Gemara before about שני חזקה shenei chazakah
is not a... is a very reasonable reinterpretation. Okay. I said, "No,
David, I'm still saying like I always said that it was my
father's, but what I meant was, you proved that it was your
father's, my father bought it from your father. Okay? That's completely reasonable.
They're both true. It's your father's and it's my father's. And the
proof is that I've been eating the שני חזקה. shenei chazakah. So
that proves that I am the most recent owner. Okay, so I'm..."
I'm accepting your witnesses. It was your father's and I'm also keeping
my claim that it was mine and I'm explaining how that's possible.
My father bought it from your father and then I inherited and
I've been here for the last three years. So even Ulla would
say that's a complete— נהרדעי Naharda'i would say that's a completely reasonable
reinterpretation and that's not a חוזר וטוען, chozer v'to'en, right? Now Tosfos
says that such a reasonable
reinterpretation, Tosfos, I don't know why we needed the Gemara to say
it. Okay, when David says it's his father and I say it's
my father, who says those are contradictory statements? Right?
I don't know how I'll figure that out.
I have to tell you, when I first heard this, it was
the first thing that occurred to me.
Who says they both can't be true? You know, because the reason
is I biased you all, I biased you all because I said
it was my ancestral plot. And the word ancestral plot means it
was always in my family and I inherited it. Okay, but that's
not and that's basically how Tosfos answers. But the simple meaning of
the word אבותיי avotai means ancestral plot. But if all I said
was, "My father owned it," and then you say, "My father owned
it," then you say, so why are those contradictory? Right? They could
have gone from hand to hand. So that's what Tosfos says. We
normally interpret the word אבותיי avotai to mean ancestral plot, but then
I'm saying, no, no, no, I meant it more literally. I meant,
you know, my father bought it from your father and therefore that
would be— so even Ulla would say that would be believed. That
is not a strong revision. It's not— it doesn't seem like it's
contradicting what was said before. Okay? והיכא דאשני מילי מעיקרא. v'heicha d'ashni
milei me'ikara. Now let's say— I'm sorry, and מהיכא דאמר ליה מעיקרא
דאבותיי והדר אמר ליה דאבותיי והיכא דאשני מילי מעיקרא ולא טעין. v'heicha
d'ashni milei me'ikara v'lo ta'ein. Now David and I were
outside of court and we were arguing about this. And David said
it's my father's field and I said it's my father's field. And
then we walked into the בית דין. Beis Din.
All this is happening outside?
Yes, all— but we were saying these claims outside: my father's and
my father's. And I did not say the claim that's going to
make me win. That's the ולא טעין v'lo ta'ein again is the
final claim, the claim that I bought it from you. ואתא לבי
דינא וטען. v'ata l'vei dina v'ta'an. Now we walk into court. David
says it's my father's field and all of a sudden I change
my tune and I say I bought it from you and I've
been here שני חזקה. shne chazaka. So is that a חוזר וטוען?
chozer v'to'en? Okay, I never took back what I said in court.
I changed the claim I was making outside of court. Now what
you could say is that— okay, well let's see what the Gemara
says.
So מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? That everybody would say is okay, even
נהרדעי. Naharda'i. דחוזר וטוען. d'chozer v'to'en. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why? עביד
איניש דלא מגלי טענתיה אלא לבי דינא. avid inish d'la megali ta'anteih
ela l'vei dina. I'm not going to let you know what I'm
going to claim. I'm going to pretend I'm going to say one
thing outside of court, get you thinking one thing, and then when
we come to court I'm going to make my real claim. Even
if I'm being total— again, the presumption is I'm being totally honest
in court and I'm doing my sort of misleading outside of court.
Right? Now of course you could have a different interpretation. Right? I
was being— sort of making certain claims outside. I was getting a
sense where David was heading, and that allowed me to shape my
claims in court, and my claims in court are also dishonest. Okay,
but we're saying no, no, we're not going to presume that. So
anyway, it is a problem about retracting a claim you made, an
official claim you made in court. What you said outside, that could
have just been strategy, and we're not going to hold you responsible
to that.
And even נהרדעי Naharda'i agrees.
Even נהרדעי Naharda'i agrees to that.
Okay, now אמר אמימר אנא נהרדעי אנא. amar Ameimar ana Naharda'i ana.
I have to tell you, I'm from נהרדעי Naharda'i who says you're
not חוזר וטוען, chozer v'to'en, but I take— I take issue with
it. וסבירא לי דחוזר וטוען. v'svira li d'chozer v'to'en. I feel you
should be allowed to reinterpret your claim. והלכתא טוען וחוזר וטוען. v'hilchasa
to'en v'chozer v'to'en. You can reinterpret your claim again unless it's like
blatantly contradicting what you said before. But even a more radical
reinterpretation— אבותיי avotai doesn't literally mean אבותיי, avotai, it means I feel
confident about it, which seems a pretty hard stretch. Again, since you've
got the evidence that can back you up, we allow that claim
to be revised in that way. Okay, now David, we're all dying
to hear, right? What's the story about that in court?
So I mean, as a— I mean, as an attorney can say
also, but my sense is that generally all the details can be
provided as evidence to the whoever is making the decision, but it's
not— you don't automatically reject it. Meaning the facts and circumstances associated
with the changed claim, you know, and of course the— because you're
a lawyer, you're being grilled, you can ask questions about it and
challenge the person.
Why is it now you're saying this and before you said that?
So it's all evidence to consider. The jury is given it all
and the— or the judge has to decide, consider the fact that
first he said this and then when that was challenged he changed
his story. Now he's saying this. You'll have to decide whether you
believe— which story you believe, right?
Or amending your cause of action. Right, right, right. So that's a
certain— oh, so that's true, yeah, that's a different— but
an amending your cause of action is... Different, right? That means that
you're using a different sort of legal strategy or whatever. Right, but
that's not the same as claiming a different set of facts.
But but he's pleading in the alternative?
Right,
but
yes, there is pleading in the alternative. But the question is...
Sorry Gloria, I should have gone to you too.
But the other aspect would be that once you make certain
during the early part of litigation, so you have an obligation to
provide facts as you understand them. And then it is really very
difficult to then contradict it because you've essentially testified to what things
are. And so for example if you then have like a motion
on the papers, you can't then retract what you've said previously.
Interesting. Right.
So in some ways it depends on the circumstances.
Interesting. But also but there is a difference whether the litigant is
testifying, you're saying sometimes a טענה taina is an implicit type of
testifying to certain facts.
Right. So for
example after you've filed a complaint, so then the other side asks
you for okay give us the details of the basis of your
complaint, and then the defendant can say okay judge based on what
he just said they have no claim, you can't then just say
oh now I'm going to say...
Ah so that actually is very similar to טוען וחוזר וטוען. to'en
vechozer veto'en. Yeah right, טוען וחוזר וטוען.
to'en vechozer
veto'en.
Oh that's very interesting.
Maybe what you were trying to get at.
Oh so if there was a case like this, I said it
was my ancestral plot and it was clear I was going to
lose on that basis and that was the way I had submitted
the papers and now I actually said wait wait actually no no
no I bought it, right, then that would not be accepted.
There is a point at which it is too late.
Interesting. Okay. Very interesting. All right. So now we continue.
זהו משל אבותי וזהו משל אבותי. zehu meshel avotai vezehu meshel avotai.
I say it's my father's. Now Gloria, we'll skip over, we'll go
to you because there's too many, we already יוצא yotzei the Davids.
Okay so I say it was my father's. You say Gloria that
it was your father's. Gloria says it was her father's.
אייתי סהדי דאבותיי ואכלה שני חזקה ואייתי סהדי דאכלה שני חזקה. aiti
sahedi de-avotai ve-achlah shenei chazakah ve-aiti sahedi de-achlah shenei chazakah. Now I
have witnesses that not only say that it was my father's and
again here there's no question of who bought it from whom. The
witnesses are directly going to contradict. I have a set of witnesses
that says it was always in Dov's family for generations and the
same witnesses also say plus he's been eating the produce for the
last three years. Okay. ואייתי סהדי דאכלה שני חזקה. ve-aiti sahedi de-achlah
shenei chazakah. Now did I read that right... and now
Gloria has witnesses that directly contradict and say Gloria's been eating the
last three years. Okay so there's this whole contradiction of witnesses. They're
straightly
in conflict with one another. So אמר רב נחמן אוקי אכילה לבהדי
אכילה ואוקי ארעא בחזקת אבותיה. amar Rav Nachman okei achilah le-bahadi achilah
ve-okei ara be-chezkat avosa.
So
okay, so the contradictory claims of who's eaten the last three years
neutralize and I'm left with the legitimate testimony that has not been
contradicted that it's my ancestral plot. Okay. אמר ליה רבא. amar lei
Rava. Rava says what are you talking about here? There's clearly somebody
lying. So היי עדות מוכחשת היא. hai edut mukcheshet hi. The testimony
is contradicted and we throw out the whole testimony. Okay. Since my
witnesses, it wasn't two separate sets of witnesses. One set of witnesses
said Dov's ancestral plot and he's been here three years. Half of
that testimony has been thrown out, the other half gets thrown out
as well. Okay. אמר ליה amar lei whether you can have partial
testimony?
Yeah, so there's a lot of things here פלגינן דיבורא. palginan dibura.
Right. Those types of questions. Right. So אמר ליה amar lei and
the question also here is are we throwing it out based on
the fact that we look at the testimony as a unit and
we either take the whole thing or throw
part of it, that's פלגינן דיבורא, palginan dibura, or maybe we throw
it out because of impugning the honesty of the witness? Since we
have a serious suspicion here, we know one set of witnesses is
lying, and 50% chance it's Dov's set of witnesses. So it's not
because the testimony is thrown out, it's because the witnesses are thrown
out and everything they say is thrown out. Okay. So אמר ליה
amar lei so Rav Nachman said back to Rava נהי דאיתכחש באכילתא
באבותא מי איתכחש? nehi de-itkachash be-achilata be-avota mi itkachash? It's true that
they were contradicted in the testimony of the eating of the years
of חזקה, chazakah,
but nobody contradicted what they said about the other part, about the
part about its ancestral plot which means two things. As far as
the testimony is concerned, a type of פלגינן דיבורא, palginan dibura, we
can accept half the testimony without the other half. As far as
the honesty and integrity of the witnesses are concerned, as we're going
to see in a minute, this is an idea of like the
witnesses have a חזקת כשרות. chezkat kashrut.
Okay. Somebody is lying but we cannot directly identify who is and
therefore we should presume in areas that they're not contradicted that everybody.
that you're the honest group, you're the honest pair. If the other
pair was to testify about something else, we would presume that they
were the honest pair. Everybody retains their חזקה Chazaka since we don't
know who's lying, their חזקה Chazaka of being honest. Okay, so גמרא
Gemara says לימא רב נחמן בפלוגתא דרב הונא ורב חסדא
קמיפלגי, Leima Rav Nachman Biflugta DeRav Huna VeRav Chisda Kamiflagi, this question
whether witnesses who have been contradicted will they be believed on something
else? Let's say that's the debate of רב הונא Rav Huna and
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. ואיתמר Ve'itmar was taught, בי תרי ובי תרי
דמכחשי אהדדי, Bei Trei Uvei Trei Demachashi Ahadadi,
you have two pairs of witnesses that directly contradict one another. They
make direct claims that are in direct contradiction. This is not עדים
זוממים. Edim Zomemim. עדים זוממים Edim Zomemim is group one says we
saw ראובן Reuven borrow money from שמעון Shimon on Monday at 2:00
PM and group two says how could you have said that Monday
at 2:00 PM, we were all together at the movies?
Okay,
so that's עדים זוממים. Edim Zomemim. But no, but what saying is
they say Monday at 2:00 PM we saw ראובן Reuven borrow money
from שמעון Shimon and the other group says how could you say
that, Monday at 2:00 PM we were with ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon at the movies? Okay, so they're directly contradicting but you're not
claiming that the witnesses were somewhere else, you're claiming that the facts
of that time and what happened there were in dispute. Okay, or
we say no, we were at that corner where you're saying that
this happened and nothing happened at that corner and they weren't around.
Okay, so they're direct contradiction with one another. אמר רב הונא זו
באה בפני עצמה ומעידה וזו באה בפני עצמה ומעידה. Amar Rav Huna
Zo Ba'ah Bifnei Atzmah Ume'idah Vezo Ba'ah Bifnei Atzmah Ume'idah. So each
one retains their presumption of being kosher witnesses. Okay, obviously you can't
accept either testimony about this case, but the fact that we know
one of them is lying, but since we don't know which one,
each set remains kosher witnesses. Okay, and they can each testify on
some other case. Now, what's the one thing that they can't do?
Okay, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon were כת Kat number one, לוי
Levi and יהודה Yehuda were כת Kat number two. They contradict, we
can't accept either. In some other case
moving forward, if ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon ever come before us,
we'll still assume they're kosher witnesses. If לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda
come before us, we'll still assume they're kosher witnesses and we'll accept
their testimony. But can you imagine one כת עדים Kat Eidim that
will not be accepted in the future?
Nope. You got ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon
were כת Kat number one and לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda were
כת Kat number two. One of these groups were lying, we don't
know which one. In the future, yes, what we won't accept in
the future is if שמעון Shimon and לוי Levi come together, right?
Or שמעון Shimon and יהודה, Yehuda, whatever, one of each. Because then
we know we're dealing with one עד Eid who is a liar.
Okay, but when we're not, when we're dealing with them separately, we're
going to assume that each one is still kosher, each group is
still kosher. Okay.
If somebody is convicted as an עד זומם, Eid Zomem, yeah, so
they can never bear testimony again in any case?
Well, there's always תשובה, Tshuva, but that's a different story. But they're
פסול Pasul until they do תשובה. Tshuva. And how you measure תשובה
Tshuva in a way that's not between you and God, but between
you and the community, that's a different story. Anyway, גמרא Gemara says
like this, זו באה בפני עצמה ומעידה וזו באה בפני עצמה ומעידה.
Zo Ba'ah Bifnei Atzmah Ume'idah Vezo Ba'ah Bifnei Atzmah Ume'idah. רב חסדא
אמר בהדי סהדי שקרי למה לי, Rav Chisda Amar Bahadi Sahadi Shikrei
Lama Li, what do I need, why should I have any truck
with—I so rarely have an opportunity to say
'truck with'—with lying witnesses? Which basically means, like, there's a cloud of
suspicion over each group, and we will not, even though I don't
know anyone is lying and in general I believe in an idea
of a חזקה Chazaka and חזקת כשרות Chazkas Kashrus and all of
that, but a court cannot accept witnesses who have had their honesty
questioned,
thrown into question. Okay, so therefore we do not accept them. All
right, going forward. So now גמרא Gemara says like this, לימא רב
נחמן דאמר כרב הונא, Leima Rav Nachman De'amar KeRav Huna, רב נחמן
Rav Nachman who says that we're going to accept the testimony about
the ancestral plot even though they were contradicted about the years of
חזקה, Chazaka, he's saying like רב הונא, Rav Huna, that we'll accept
each group on a different matter. So okay, they were contradicted about
the חזקה Chazaka years but we're going to accept their testimony on
the ancestral plot. So that's like רב הונא Rav Huna that says
they can come separately. ורבא כרב חסדא, VeRava KeRav Chisda, and רבא
Rava is like רב חסדא Rav Chisda that says once the cloud
of suspicion is over their heads, we're not going to accept them
about anything. So that seems like a reasonable way of linking it
up. So גמרא Gemara says no, אליבא דרב חסדא כולי עלמא לא
פליגי, Aliba DeRav Chisda Kulei Alma Lo Pligi, according to רב חסדא
Rav Chisda who says that they cannot be testify in the future,
so of course, if they can't testify in the future, they certainly
can't testify on this case itself about the ancestral plot and so
on. So according רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, of course, you can't accept
them. כי פליגי אליבא דרב הונא, Ki Pligi Aliba DeRav Huna, the
question is working within רב הונא Rav Huna who's willing to accept
contradictory witnesses, you know, in this case of two pairs that contradict,
willing to accept each one individually in a different case. So רב
נחמן כרב הונא, Rav Nachman KeRav Huna, רב נחמן Rav Nachman says
that's what I'm saying, the
testifying about the ancestral עד כאן לא קאמר רב הונא אלא בעדות
אחרת. Ad kan lo ka'amar Rav Huna ela b'edut acheret. When did
רב הונא Rav Huna say
that? Wait, did I skip a line? Okay. When did רב הונא
Rav Huna say that you can go ahead and you know they
retain their חזקת כשרות chazkas kashrus even though somebody was lying, each
one taken separately is assumed to be כשר kosher and you can
accept their testimony in a different matter? That's a different matter, עדות
אחרת. edut acheret. אבל לאותו עדות לא! Aval l'oto edut lo! But
for this testimony, no. For this testimony, the cloud of suspicion remains
over their heads you know in this testimony. Now again you could
say that in two ways. You could say it's not about them
בגברא, b'gavra, whether they're כשר, kosher, it's about the testimony. The testimony
is a unit. So since they've been found out to be lying
in, or not lying, since the question has been raised whether they're
lying in order to support my claim that it's my land, any
testimony about my land, it's all one unit of testimony and it
all gets thrown out. So it gets thrown out like a לא
פלגינן דיבורא. lo palginan dibburei. We throw out part of the testimony,
we're gonna throw out the whole thing. Or, it could be about
them in their, not about the testimony as a unit, but about
them as כשר kosher witnesses, right? For this case, their honesty is
being questioned, right? This case, we have the question mark over their
honesty and you know and therefore anything related to this case we
can't accept them. Okay, so that's anyway רבא's Rava point. Maybe I'll
accept them for a different case, but for the same case, once
there's been a contradiction, I can't accept anything they said in this
case. Yes.
So why is it a problem for ראובן Reuven to come with
לוי? Levi?
Because then we know that one of them was an עד שקר.
ed sheker. So we have a כת kat of two witnesses made
up of one definite עד שקר. ed sheker. We can't identify which
one, but you know we don't have two, we know for sure
we don't have two כשר kosher witnesses here. Okay. Once somebody has
testified falsely in court, let me clarify this, okay, then they are
פסול pasul for future עדות. edut. Okay, they're an עד שקר ed
sheker and they're פסול pasul for future עדות. edut. Okay. So in
this case where they contradicted, we know one of these groups are
עדי שקר edeis sheker and cannot be accepted in the future. We
just don't know which one. Okay, so maybe that wasn't clear before.
All right. So in this, so רבא Rava is saying look, I
get that going forward we're going to presume that each group is
כשר עדים, kosher edim, but in this case itself, okay, since the
question has been raised, I can't accept anything they said. Okay, so
that's what רבא Rava said. Yeah, you had a question חנן? Hanan?
Yeah, I don't know if it's for this case, but does the
גמרא Gemara recognize that some people just make mistakes and they might
not be?
Yes, so the גמרא Gemara definitely raises the possibility about, it's sort
of like the טוען וחוזר וטוען, ta'en v'chozer v'ta'en, how does it
work with עדים? edim? But like, no, actually the reason is that
they were misinterpreting the facts or whatever, so nobody is really lying.
Yeah, that's a possibility, definitely. That comes up particularly in גמרא ראש
השנה Gemara Rosh Hashanah about questions about exactly what time it was
before everybody had watches and their iPhones and knew the time to
the second. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay, so
apparently רב נחמן Rav Nachman won, and I'm sorry, not רב נחמן,
Rav Nachman, apparently רבא, Rava,
רבא's Rava position won. I'm sorry, wait,
wait, wait, okay, apparently, got to get this right, apparently רב נחמן
Rav Nachman won, right, let's say what we go like רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, I'm still going to
accept דוב's Dov witnesses that they were his ancestral plot. Yes, there
was a contradiction about the years of חזקה, chazaka, but we're able
to still accept them on something else and their testimony that it
was my ancestral plot is still going to win. רבא Rava got
overruled. I'm going to use my witnesses to say it was my
ancestral plot and they gave the, they awarded the field to me.
Okay. Then after they awarded the field to me based on that,
that that was the testimony that was left standing, הדר אייתי סהדי
דבסתיה. hadar aytei sahadai d'vasteihi. Then Gloria found witnesses that it was
her ancestral plot. Okay, so here we go, we're contradicting witnesses. So,
so now we got to do something about this. We can't let
it remain in my possession.
Nah, so אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav
Nachman said, אנא נחתינן אנא מסקינן, ana nacheitnan ana maskinan, we brought
דוב Dov down to the field, like you know, that means we
awarded the field to דוב, Dov, we will take him away from
the field, we will revoke our, we will reverse our decision, מסקינן
ליה, maskinan lei, וזילותא דבי דינא לא חיישינן. v'zilusa d'bei dina lo
chaishinan. We're not afraid that people are going to say oh, this
court doesn't know what they're doing, right, for one minute they give
it to דוב, Dov, the next minute they take it away from
דוב, Dov, we're not afraid of that, we are more concerned with
אמת emes than with perceptions. Okay, Rabbi Weiss has a great line
which is the only difference between perceptions and the, what is it,
what is it? The only difference between perceptions and the facts is
that it's easier to change facts.
So anyway, so we're not concerned with perceptions, we're concerned with the
truth, okay, and therefore we're going to now change our judgment even
though people will say oh, the court is irresponsible, they don't know
what they're doing. Now, I want to make an important point, this
issue of are you חייש... chaish... Are you חיישינן לזילותא דבי דינא
haishinan l'ziluta d'bei dina and are you willing to reverse your judgment?
You know, you should assume this—first of all, you should assume it's
a large question. It should come up all the time. We have
new evidence. Are we willing
to rejudge the case? Right? I mean, in secular court, you could
bring tons of evidence that proves that the court was wrong and
new evidence or whatever, right? And that's not a basis for appeal.
Basis of appeal has to be procedural. Is that correct? Well, okay,
criminal. All right, fine. Anyway, but
it's not often enough to bring a lot of new evidence, even
if it's very strong evidence. Okay? But so that's the point. You
know what? Judgments have to be final. Okay. But there also could
be differences in terms of what the new judgment is. This case,
now Gloria has her witnesses, so what's going to be the new
judgment? Everything is contradictory right now. So you know what the new
judgment is going to be? The new judgment is going to be—the
Rashbam says כל דאלים גבר. kol d'alim gvar. Basically, the new judgment
is going to be: We can't figure out who's it is, you
guys fight it out. Now, whatever exactly כל דאלים גבר kol d'alim
gvar is, we won't worry about right now. But the point is,
but the point is, it's much more זילותא דבי דינא ziluta d'bei
dina if they're not just taking it away from me, but they're
just sort of throwing up their hands and they're not even awarding
it to anybody. Right? That really says, like, they have no idea
what they're doing, right? You know? So we'd much rather leave it
in Dov's hands where it might be Dov's anyway—we don't have evidence
that it's Gloria's. We just now know that it's all neutralized. So
better to leave it in Dov's hand, where A, it might be
his anyway, and B, you know, the alternative
is—is not a פסק, psak, the alternative is just a question mark.
Okay. But it's—it would be very different if we had clear evidence
that it was Gloria's. Then A, they wouldn't want to leave it
in my hands because it clearly wasn't mine, so it would be
more a sense of a perversion of justice. And B, awarding it
to Gloria would not look so bad. At least in the end
it ended with something concrete, it ended with a real alternative judgment.
So the idea here of זילותא דבי דינא ziluta d'bei dina is
very heightened because A, they might still be right, it might still
be mine, and B, the reversal does not replace a definite פסק
psak with a question mark as opposed to replacing a definite judgment
with a different definite judgment.
Yes, and the concern is that people will not appreciate how nuanced
the beis din has to be in discerning really... Right.
But could you—what is—how do you translate אחתיניה? achitnei?
We brought him down to the field, meaning we awarded the field
to him. Imagine we're here in court and...
yes, literally means we lowered him and we raised him up, but
lowered is not a bad thing here. It means you allowed me
to descend into the field and take possession of the field. Now
we are going to remove me from the field. Okay, that's אסיקניה.
asiknei. We will bring him down, we will take him away, זילותא
דבי דינא לא חיישינן. ziluta d'bei dina lo haishinan. We're not going
to be concerned that what people are going to say, that beis
din doesn't know what they're doing. Now, מתיב רבא ואי תימא רב
זירא. mative Rava ve-i teima Rav Zeira. Now Rava asks, and some
say Rav Zeira: Is it really true we're not concerned about the—about
the, you know, the ill repute of the
beis din? שנים אומרים מת ושנים אומרים לא מת. shenayim omrim met
u-shenayim omrim lo met. Two witnesses say this woman's husband died, and
two say she did not die, and she wants to go ahead
and remarry. שנים אומרים נתגרשה ושנים אומרים לא נתגרשה. shenayim omrim nitgareshah
u-shenayim omrim lo nitgareshah. And two say she was divorced, and two
say not. It's another issue about contradictory witnesses. הרי זו לא תנשא.
harei zu lo tinase. She can't get married because maybe she's still
married to her first husband. ואם נשאת לא תצא. ve-im niset lo
tetze. But if she does, because the witnesses contradict and there's a
big question mark, we allow the situation to remain as it is,
we don't force her to reverse, which is a big question mark.
Why don't we say she has a חזקת אשת איש? chezkat eshet
ish?
She's presumed married until there's direct evidence otherwise. But okay, because of
the contradictory witnesses, we let it stand. Okay. רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי
אומר. Rabbi Menachem b'Rabbi Yosi omer. Rabbi Menachem bar Rabbi Yosi says
תצא. tetze. No, she has to get—she has to leave her second
husband because, you know, once the witnesses have neutralized, she's still a
presumed אשת איש. eshet ish. אמר רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי. amar Rabbi
Menachem b'Rabbi Yosi. Now said Rabbi Menachem bar Rabbi Yosi: אימתי אני
אומר תצא? eimatai ani omer tetze? When do I say she has
to leave her second husband? בזמן שבאו עדים ואחר כך נישאת. bizman
she-bau edim ve-achar kach niset. If first the contradictory witnesses came that
said that she was still married, and then the court basically told
her you're not allowed to get married, and then she ignored us
and she went out and got married. So she was in direct
violation of the court after the witnesses that said she was still
married had come. Okay? And then we're going to not tolerate that
situation. We're going to demand she gets divorced. Okay.
אבל, aval, but נישאת—let's niset say there were witnesses that her husband
died and she went ahead and we פסקנו paskened she could get
married, and she got married. Everything was legitimate. ואחר כך באו עדים,
ve-achar kach bau edim, and now witnesses have come and said he
didn't die. So in that case הרי זו לא תצא. harei zu
lo tetze. She did nothing wrong and we're not going to make
her leave. Okay. Now again, the point is: But one minute, why
don't you still make her leave? Like, you know, she still has
a חזקת אשת איש chezkat eshet ish and so on. So the
point is, this is a type of a זילותא דבי דינא, ziluta
d'bei dina, right? Which is like—which is that, okay, but she got
married legitimately, we gave a definite פסק psak she could. get married.
Notice also the parallel here, that the new פסק psak is not
necessarily the opposite פסק, psak, the new פסק psak is a question
mark. Right? Do you see the parallel? The new פסק psak is
contradictory witnesses we don't know. So therefore we have to take it
out from a definite פסק psak to a we don't know hands
off don't do anything? Right? No, let's just leave things the way
they are. Okay. Question. Actually,
well, so תוספות Tosafos asks that if she had to actually get
married, why wasn't it enough that they just פסק paskened that she
get married? So that's a good point, but we're not going to
go into that. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, so אמר amar
so הרי זו לא תצא. harei zu lo teitzei. So you see
that where were we, that we are concerned for זילותא דבי דינא.
zilusa de'bei dina. We don't say take her out. We say let
her stay. Okay. And we're sort of ignoring the whole human dimension
here as well, which could be a factor. Okay, obviously what does
it mean to make a woman divorce? Remarried. So therefore רבא Rava
says to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, you're saying after a פסק psak
we would reverse it even in this case where all you have
is a contradiction and a ספק. safek. That's exactly this case of
the woman getting married and contradictory witnesses, and we don't reverse it,
we let things stand. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said
back to him, אנא סברי למעבד עובדא. ana savari lemiavad uvda. I
was going to פסק pasken like I thought, I was going to
reverse the פסק psak and take the field away from the guy
now that there are contradictory witnesses. השתא דאותבינן את, hasha de'osvinan at,
now that you've challenged that idea from this case of what do
you call it, of the חכמים Chachamim and רבי מנחם, Rabbi Menachem,
ואותבינן רב המנונא בסוריא ve'osvanan Rav Hamnuna be'Surya and רב המנונא Rav
Hamnuna in סוריא Surya also challenged me on a similar basis and
they said this proves that you let the פסק psak stand, you
don't reverse the פסק. psak. So in that case לא עבידנא בעובדא,
lo avidina ba'uvda, fine, I'm going to let it stand, I concede
it. Now of course there are ways you can distinguish the case
and the most powerful one, well there's both לקולא lekula and לחומרא,
lechumra, the most powerful one לקולא lekula why we want to let
it stand is there's a human being here who got into a
marriage and whatever, what tragedy would be of the divorce. The flip
side is that there's more of a reason in that case to
make her divorce because there's a concern about adultery and אשת איש
eishes ish and she has a חזקת אשת איש. chazakas eishes ish.
So okay, you could make distinctions. But anyway, that seemed at least
to be a similar case to say we don't reverse it and
certainly when all you have now is a ספק, safek, we're not
going to reverse it and therefore רב נחמן Rav Nachman says fine
I won't reverse it I was going to but I won't reverse
it. After making when and after making that announcement so he says,
נפיק עבד עובדא. nafik avad uvda. He made the announcement fine I'm
not going to do anything and then he went out and he
did what he wanted to do all along okay and he went
out and he took the field away from him because there were
now new contradictory
witnesses okay and then so I just want to read so the
גמרא Gemara says מאן דחזא, man d'chaza, somebody saw that רב נחמן
Rav Nachman went ahead and reversed his פסק psak after he said
he was going to let the matter stay, סבר טעות הוא בידיה.
savar taus hu biyadei. He made a mistake, like he forgot about
all of this evidence that was just brought, so טעות הוא בידיה.
taus hu biyadei. ולא היא, ve'lo hi, אלא משום דתליא באשלי רברבי.
ela bishum de'talya ba'aflei ravrevei. It's not that he made a mistake,
it's that he supported himself with like big oak trees, meaning after
he had this contradiction that רבא Rava presented, he was able to
find evidence to support his position and what we'll see tomorrow is
what evidence רב נחמן Rav Nachman found to say that a בית
דין beis din will reverse itself and is not concerned for זילותא
דבי דינא. zilusa de'bei dina. Yes Gloria, you had a question.
Having contradictory witnesses, do you just sort of say okay we're stuck?